<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three letters tending to demonstrate how the security against al future persecution for religion lys in the abolishment of the present penal laws and tests, and in the establishment of a new law for universal liberty of conscience</title>
            <author>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6978</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12193330</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12193330</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 872:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three letters tending to demonstrate how the security against al future persecution for religion lys in the abolishment of the present penal laws and tests, and in the establishment of a new law for universal liberty of conscience</title>
                  <author>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold, by Andrew Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to William Penn. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Imprint for colophon.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55930:1"/>
            <head>THREE LETTERS Tending to demonſtrate how the <hi>Security of this Nation</hi> Againſt al Future Perſecution for Religion, Lys in the Aboliſhment of the Preſent Penal Laws and Teſts, and in the Eſtabliſhment of A New Law for Univerſal Liberty of Conſcience.</head>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>With Allowance.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>The Firſt Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>UPon the receipt of your laſt Letter, I was, at firſt, a little troubled to perceiv the cenſorious Judgment you paſs upon my Politics, in reference to the grand buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Liberty of Conſcience. But after a little conſideration I comforted my ſelf. For I not onely remembred your conſtant favorable regard towards thoſe of different Perſwaſions from yours, but I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved alſo, even in that very Letter, that you agree with me in this Fundamental Principle, That <hi>no Man ought to be Perſecuted for Matters of meer Religion.</hi> And this agreement in ſo great a Principle made me hope that, notwithſtanding our preſent Difference, it would be no hard matter for you and me to agree in our particular Concluſions, and conſequently in our Conduct. To procure that Agreement there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing requiſite but <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Senſe.</hi> Let us but examin thorowly whither that Principle leads, and let us be tru to the reſult of our own Examinations, and the Work wil be don.</p>
               <p>But perhaps ſo ſtrict a ſubjection as this to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of that Principle, however juſt and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in it ſelf, may ſeem unto you a little unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in this Conjuncture. Nay I muſt acknowledg to you, that I my ſelf alſo am not ſo much Maſter of my Paſſions, as to let Reaſon have always that abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Dominion that belongs to it. The fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceived, by a Party of Men who plead for Liberty, makes me ſomtimes doubtful in determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon the practice of what I acknowledg to be a Duty. I am convinced that the <hi>Intereſt of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as wel as the <hi>Laws of Chriſtianity,</hi> requires an <hi>Abſolute, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal, Equal, and Inviolable Liberty of Conſcience.</hi> Nothing that dos not tend to the Ruin of the Government, or to the Prejudice of the People, which is but one and the ſame thing, ſhould be made the occaſion of laying any Reſtraint upon any Man. But where I ſee ground to fear that the granting of this Liberty ſhould ſerv onely to put a Power into their Hands that now demand it, wherby they may be able hereafter to take it away from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, truly in that caſe I am apt to heſitate upon the Point; or to ſay better, I confeſs that I heſitate not at al. For I would by no means that a ſpecious hope of Chriſtian Liberty ſhould betray the Nation into a New Unchriſtian Slavery.</p>
               <p>Thus far I am ſure I agree with you. We would have <hi>Liberty with Security of its continuance: not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.</hi> Now I intreat you to examin whether or no, in the reſt, you agree with me. I ask then, if ſo be it can be demonſtrated that the Penal Laws, and Teſts too, may be taken away without expoſing the Nation to any hazard of Perſecution by the <hi>Roman Catholics;</hi> Nay, if a <hi>far better Security</hi> may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt that Perſecution that thoſe preſent Laws and Teſts do afford us; wil it not be an Act of Equity and Wiſdom, as wel as Chriſtianity, in that caſe, to aboliſh them? This Security being ſuppoſed, nothing can hinder us from complying with that Deſign, but ſuch Conſiderations as ariſe from the <hi>Covetouſneſs and Ambition</hi> of ingroſſing al Honorable and Profitable Imployments unto our ſelvs, and thoſe of our own Perſwaſion. But wil any Conſiderations of that Nature, when they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere with a Public Intereſt and an avowed Duty, be juſtifiable, or even excuſable, either before God or Man? I cannot doubt but your determination in that Point alſo wil be the ſame with mine. Thoſe Conſiderations are too ſordid to be of any weight with an Honeſt Mind.</p>
               <p>Your Objection, I know, in reading theſe Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wil ariſe from a <hi>Diſſidence</hi> that any new Security of this Nature, either wil or can be granted us. There indeed perhaps you and I may differ in our opinions. But however, to com as near as we can, I wil at preſent ſuſpend my own Hopes, and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with your Doubts, conſider onely what is our Duty, and the Duty of al honeſt Men, even in this ſuppoſed doubtful Conjuncture.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55930:2"/>
               <p>An Example in the like caſe, not many years ago, when the Nation was in as great a ferment as it is now, may direct us. Thoſe that ſuppoſed there could be no other real Security, againſt the fears that poſſeſt them, than that <hi>Odious Bil of Excluſion</hi> which they promoted in Parliament, profeſſed nevertheleſs their conſtant willingneſs to liſten unto any Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients that ſhould be offered for that purpoſe. If they did not then comply with any of thoſe Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, it was the heat of Faction that hindred them; and they have ſince on al occaſions acknowledged their Error. Let us therfore proſit by their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Let us imitate them in that reaſonable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition which they profeſt, and be careful to avoid thoſe heats which cauſed their actual miſcarriage.</p>
               <p>In a word: Let us, at leaſt, <hi>put the Thing to a Trial.</hi> Let it be referred to the Wiſdom of a <hi>Parliament</hi> to weight the <hi>Expedients</hi> that may be invented or offered for our Security. Let <hi>Moderate Men</hi> be choſen into that Parliament; and not ſuch as ar ingaged, by a long habit of Perſecuting, to keep up the preſent Penal Laws, as Tools already ſitted for their Hands. Til we be called to that <hi>Election-Work,</hi> let us each of us endeavor to diſpoſe our Selvs, diſpoſe One A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and as occaſion offers diſpoſe our Friends, to that <hi>Spirit of Wiſdom and Moderation</hi> which is now ſo neceſſary. And til this Buſineſs have been weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Parliament, let us a little <hi>ſuſpend</hi> our Judgment upon it, and have always a great care that we <hi>obſtruct not the Good we deſire</hi> by heightning any doubtful Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſys to an irreconcilable Extremity.</p>
               <p>Theſe ar the Rules of my Politics, which I hope you wil now look upon a little more favorably then you ſeemed to do in your laſt Letter. At preſent I wil trouble you no further. But if what I have now ſaid prove acceptable, I ſhal be very ready, upon your deſire, to explain further my inmoſt thoughts upon any the niceſt Circumſtances of this great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair. I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>The Second Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am heartily glad that my laſt Letter has given you any meaſure of Satisfaction. But I perceiv by your new Quaerys, that I have ingaged my ſelf, in the cloſe of that Letter, to a greater Task than I was aware of. It is not enough, it ſeems, to have ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd you ſo far as I have gon, but I muſt either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu to anſwer your new Difficultys, or elſe joyn with you in owning them to be unanſwerable. I muſt either ſhew you the very <hi>Expedients</hi> that may be contrived for ſecuring us againſt any future Peeſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the <hi>Roman Catholics,</hi> or elſe acknowledg that no ſuch thing either can or wil be don. That is a little hard. The thing may be feizable, tho I ſhould not be able to demonſtrate it. Others may know more than I can. Nay indeed, the truth is that I know ſo little, and others have already ſaid ſo much upon this Subject, that, as I cannot pretend to make any new diſcoverys in it, ſo neither am I willing to repeat juſt the ſame things that you have read elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: And between thoſe two Difficulties I am ſomthing ſtraitned in complying with what you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Nevertheleſs ſince I am ingaged, I wil rather hazard to repeat what may have been hinted at al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready by others, than refuſe to explain unto you my own Conceptions.</p>
               <p>The Security we demand muſt be conſidered either as it lys naturally <hi>in the Thing it ſelf;</hi> I mean in the <hi>Repeal</hi> of al Old Penal Laws and Teſts; and in the <hi>Sanction</hi> of a New Great Charter for Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; or elſe as it may be fortify'd by ſuch <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients</hi> as the Wiſdom of a <hi>Parliament</hi> may think fit to propound, and His <hi>Majeſtys Goodneſs</hi> may vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to grant,</p>
               <p>But this laſt Conſideration belongs not to my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. It becoms not private Perſons to anticipate Parliamentary Deliberations, much leſs to preſcribe Rules unto His Majeſtys Conduct. It ſuffices me, in that reſpect, to know that His Majeſty has been pleaſed, <hi>by often reiterated Promiſes,</hi> to aſſure us that he wil concur with his Parliament, in any thing that may be reaſonably offered for the Eſtabliſhment of ſuch <hi>a Law of Chriſtian Liberty as may never be broken.</hi> I am not curious to pry further into thoſe matters, until his His Majeſty ſhal think fit in his Wiſdom to diſcloſe unto the Nation the Treaſures of his Goodneſs. And to ſpeak freely to you, as a Friend, I am yet the leſs curious about it at this time, nor any ways impatient to know more, until a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be ready to deliberate thereupon; becauſe I know already, that there ar a ſort of Men in the Nation who watch upon every occaſion, with al the Arts that Malice can invent, to blaſt any thing that ſhal be offered for the advancement of this Chriſtian Deſign. Leaving therfore the conſideration of this <hi>Acceſſional Security</hi> that we look for, I wil now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my ſelf to conſider onely what proſpect of Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the Thing it ſelf dos <hi>in its own Nature</hi> afford us.</p>
               <p>When we diſcourſe about this Security, I ſuppoſe we both of us underſtand it onely with relation to the hazard that may ariſe from taking away the Teſts. For as to the Penal Laws, ſingly conſidered, I think al Men that have Souls large enough (as I am ſure you have) to prefer the <hi>General Good</hi> of their Country before the <hi>Narrow Advantages</hi> of a Party, wil agree that it is no leſs the Intereſt of this Nation to aboliſh them, than the Duty of al Mankind to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear Perſecution.</p>
               <p>There is no hazard in the aboliſhment of thoſe Penal Laws. Now what the hazard may be in abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing the Teſts, wil be beſt perceived by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Effect of their impoſition. The Effect, in which the Proteſtant Intereſt conſiſts, is that the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> ar therby excluded from al <hi>Places of Public Truſt,</hi> either Civil or Military. This, I ſhould have ſaid, is the Intent of them. But how far the real Effect fals ſhort of that Intent, and how far it muſt needs ſal ſhort therof in the Reign of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Prince, is too evident to need any demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nevertheleſs, ſuppoſing that the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics</hi> were indeed therby debard from entring into any Public Imployments, What is the advantage, I beſeech you, that Proteſtants, or that the Nation in general, pretend to receiv by their Excluſion? I know you wil tel me that we have therby our Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt that Principle of <hi>Perſecution</hi> which we think inſeparably joyned to <hi>their Religion.</hi> They wil not be able to impoſe their Religion upon us, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute us for not receiving it. That is the tru End, &amp; we wil ſuppoſe it to be the real Effect of the Teſts.</p>
               <p>You do not pretend ſure that the Excluſion of the Roman Catholics from ſuch Imployments is any Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55930:2"/>to our <hi>Civil Rights,</hi> or to the <hi>Fundamental Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> of our Government. They ar Engliſh Men as wel as we. The Civil Rights of Engliſh Men ought to be no leſs dear to them than to us. And if thy malicious Surmizer ſhould preſume to imagin that His Majeſty had a deſign to raiſe his own Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative upon the ruin of the Peoples Libertys; we have reaſon to believ, by many paſt inſtances, that Men of another Religion, much more numerous and powerful than the Roman Catholics, would be found no leſs ready Inſtruments, but far more proper ones, for the effecting of that work. The beſt defence that I know againſt thoſe imaginary fears, and the moſt becoming dutiful Subjects, is to comply chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with his Majeſty in al things reaſonable; that ſo an unreaſonable Refuſal may not force him upon new Methods, and make us feel in the end what we ar perhaps too ſlow to conceiv, that <hi>Omnia dat qui justa negat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I return to the conſideration of our being ſecured againſt Perſecution by the Excluſion of the Roman Catholics from Public Imployments. In very good time, that the <hi>Church of England</hi> now looks for ſuch a Security! I am ſure others have not been ſecured againſt it, by the public adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Members. However, let us conſider how it is that the Teſts ſecure us, or how it is that they hinder them from entering into thoſe Imployments. It is not as a Wal or Barricado that confines them to a certain Incloſure, out of which they cannot move; nor is it as a Charm or Spel that, by any Magic Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, hinders them from acting. It is onely as <hi>a Law,</hi> which, by the penalty annexed to it, aws their Minds, and makes them fearful to tranſgreſs it. They dar not enter into Public Offices, leſt they ſhould be puniſhed for the <hi>Breach of that Law</hi> which forbids them to do it. But, pray, Who is it that ſhould puniſh them for that Offence? They know very wel that in this Reign they ar in no danger. That Law is now diſpenſed with. The onely Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle therfore that reſtrains them from tranſgreſſing it, is evidently the fear of its being revived in the Reign of the next Succeſſor; becauſe it is a Law whoſe Penalty they wil be always liable unto, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Government ſhal think fit to exact it.</p>
               <p>Now if this be the onely Ground of their Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from Public Offices, and conſequently of our pretended Security; I ſay, if it be onely the <hi>Force of a Law</hi> that works that effect; pray let us conſider if <hi>another Law</hi> might not be contrived, to ſecure us much more effectually againſt Perſecution, than this Excluſion of them either dos or can do.</p>
               <p>Let us therfore have <hi>a Law</hi> enacted, which, in <hi>Aboliſhing al thoſe Penal Ones, and al the Tests too</hi> that ar now complained of, ſhal <hi>Eſtabliſh a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal and Equal Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> as a Magna Charta of Religion, with al the ingaging Circumſtances that the Wit of Man can invent to make it inviolable. Let that <hi>Liberty</hi> be declared to be the <hi>Natural Right of Al Men,</hi> and any violation therof be therfore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Criminal. Let not onely every <hi>Actual Infringment</hi> of that Law, but every <hi>Motion, Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Contrivance,</hi> expreſt either in Word or Deed, tending any way to the invalidating of it, be eſteemed &amp; declared to be an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndermining of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Constitution of our Government,</hi> &amp; according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be made puniſhable with the utmoſt Severitys, even as <hi>Felony</hi> or <hi>Treaſon.</hi> Let the Extent of this Law reach <hi>Al Conditions</hi> and <hi>Al Degrees</hi> of Men, Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Cavil, and Military, from the higheſt Lord to the meaneſt Beggar. Let not <hi>future Parliaments</hi> themſelvs be exempted from the danger of infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it, but let any Propoſition tending therunto, <hi>tho even in either Houſe of Parliament,</hi> be not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a Tranſgreſſion therof, but expreſly declared to be the higheſt and worſt of al Tranſgreſſions; and let no Parliamentary, or other <hi>Priviledg</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever exempt any ſuch Offender from the ſevereſt Puniſhment, no more than they can do it now from that of Treaſon. And after al this, and what more the Wiſeſt Heads may invent, let <hi>The King</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be humbly beſeeched to ſuffer in it a Clauſe, by which, <hi>reſerving al other Rights of his Prerogative</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violated, he may ſolemnly <hi>renounce the onely Right of Diſpenſing with this Law, or of Pardoning any Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor of it in any caſe whatſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Suppoſing now that ſuch a Law as this ſhould be Enacted, I beſeech you to conſider if it do not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the end of ſecuring us againſt Perſecution, inſinitely better than the preſent Teſts that exclude the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> from Public Imployments. It wil <hi>ſecure,</hi> in the firſt place, <hi>al the Diſſenting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> from the preſent Penal Laws, which the Teſts do not: And it wil indeed ſecure al Partys againſt al Perſecution, in every reſpect, far better than They do. It wil do it in a <hi>direct manner:</hi> Wheras They work onely by a <hi>weak and ſtrained Conſequence.</hi> It wil do it upon the <hi>ſolid grounds of Religion, Truth, and Equity:</hi> Wheras They ar built onely upon <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious, partial, and unjust Principles.</hi> It wil be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be in its own Nature <hi>Indiſpenſable:</hi> Wheras They are every day <hi>diſpenſed with.</hi> It wil be Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by a more <hi>ſolemn Sanction.</hi> And it wil be inforced by more <hi>awful and terifying Penaltys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Advantages, as you ſee, do al appear in the ſimpleſt proſpect that we can take of <hi>the Thing it ſelf, in its own Nature;</hi> in the <hi>meer Aboliſhment,</hi> I mean, <hi>of the Laws of Perſecution, and the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Law of Liberty;</hi> without the help of any further <hi>Expedients.</hi> That is the onely thing that I propoſed to my ſelf to Explain. And I cannot but now hope that even this explanation, how imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſoever it be, wil convince you that it is not ſo <hi>dangerous</hi> a Work to <hi>aboliſh the Tests,</hi> nor ſo <hi>difficult</hi> to <hi>establiſh a lasting Security against Perſecution,</hi> when thoſe Teſts ſhal be aboliſhed, as ſom People in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly endeavor to perſwade us. But I perceiv that I have been already too tedious upon this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. Wherfore without further Application or Improvement therof, I now refer what I have ſaid to your Examination, and ſubmit it to your Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reſting always <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <head>The Third Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>RIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce I have had the good fortune to pleaſe you the ſecond time, I am reſolved to try it a third. I have endeavored, as you have ſeen, to make it appear that it is not impoſſible to contrive <hi>a more Equitable and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nexceptionable</hi> Law than the Teſts, which wil ſecure us alſo <hi>infinitely better</hi> than They do, againſt the danger of being <hi>Perſecuted by the Roman Catholics.</hi> Now you anſwer me that this Law, tho
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55930:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſhould be conſented to, would be leſs Security to us againſt the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> than the <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts:</hi> becauſe by it they would be admitted into the <hi>Legiſlative,</hi> as wel as <hi>Executive,</hi> parts of our Government; wher as by the other they are wholly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from both. And an <hi>Excluſion,</hi> ſay you, eſpecially from the Legiſlative Power, is a far better Security than any <hi>Regulation</hi> whatſoever that can be made about their Conduct in it: becauſe when once admitted into that capacity, there wil be ſtil reaſon to apprehend left they ſhould break thro the Rules preſcribed for their Conduct, and change even the Laws themſelves at their Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>This is indeed very ſpecious. But I intreat you to conſider, in the firſt place, That the <hi>Excluſion</hi> we talk of by the Teſts is onely <hi>Imaginary,</hi> not <hi>Real.</hi> We pleaſe our ſelvs with a Notion, while we ar fruſtrated of the Thing. A <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> diſſipates al that Bulwark into Duſt and Air: While on the contrary the <hi>Regulation</hi> I have propounded is to be <hi>Declared and Made</hi> abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <hi>Indiſpenſably.</hi> Which is no inconſiderable advantage on the ſide that I incline to.</p>
               <p>But this is not al. Your Objection prompts me to a further Defence of my Propoſition. Nothing wil ſerve your turn but an <hi>Abſolute Excluſion</hi> of thoſe that may have a mind <hi>to hurt us,</hi> from al manner of ſhare, either Legiſlative or Executive, in our Government. Be it ſo. I am very wel pleaſed to join Iſſu with you upon that Point.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hurt</hi> we ſear, and deſire to fence againſt, is <hi>Perſecution.</hi> Let us therfore, in Gods Name, exclude al <hi>Perſecuting Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> too, from thoſe Imployments. But let al thoſe that have a <hi>Spirit of Moderation and Charity,</hi> joyned with other neceſſary Qualifications, be promiſcuouſly admitted unto them, whatſoever be their profeſſion of Religion. It is not the Notion of Tranſubſtantiation that hurts us. Why ſhould we therſore make that the ground of an Excluſion? Let us go to the tru Ground of the Matter, and do our Work at once, effectually.</p>
               <p>In a Word: Let <hi>this Act it ſelf,</hi> that we are projecting, be the <hi>Fundamental Teſt</hi> for the Admiſſion of al Perſons into al manner of Public Imployments, or for their Excluſion from them. Let every <hi>Member of both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> before they ar ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſit there, be obliged to ſubſcribe a <hi>Declaration,</hi> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting That they <hi>ſolemnly profeſs, and, in the the preſence of God, ſincerely acknowledg the natural Equity of this Great Law; and that they in like manner promis never to infringe it, nor either directly or indirectly to promote any deſign of undermining or invalidating it in any manner whatſoever.</hi> Let al thoſe that ſhal preſume to ſit in either Houſe, without having firſt ſubſcribed that Declaration, be liable to the ſevereſt Penaltys that ſhal be annexed to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Law. And let al <hi>future Acts</hi> (if any ſuch there ſhould be) paſſed by a Parliament not ſo qualified as by this Law ſhal be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, be declared <hi>Illegal and Nul.</hi> Nay further, if it may be thought any ſtrengthning to our Security, let alſo <hi>Al other Public Officers,</hi> as wel as the Members of Parliament, be obliged, upon their entrance into thoſe Offices, to ſubſcribe the ſame ſolemn Declaration, upon the hazard of the ſame Penalties, and of the Illegality und Nullity of al their Proceedings. Let al that Govern, or Teach, or anyway Officiate <hi>in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs,</hi> either in Church or Conventicle, Al <hi>Judges, Juſtices, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Magiſtrates, Military Commanders</hi> both by Sea and Land, with al the Inferior and Subordinate Officers depending upon any of them, from the higheſt to the loweſt, be Al ſubject to the ſame Rule.</p>
               <p>This is the <hi>Teſt againſt Perſecution</hi> that we have been long ſince adviſed too, by One of the earlieſt and ſtrongeſt Writers upon this Subject; but which the Nation ſeems not yet to have enough reflected upon. If this be not judged a ſufficient Security, I wiſh thoſe that perceiv the defects of it would propound unto us any thing better. I ſhal be always for chuſing the beſt. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, in the mean while, I think al Men muſt agree that, <hi>if it be indeed Perſecution that we deſire to fence againſt,</hi> this is infinitely a Better Security in that reſpect than the preſent Penal Laws and Teſts ar. And therfore, <hi>provided this may be granted,</hi> I cannot but yet hope that there wil appear to be among us Men Wiſe enough, and Honeſt enough, and thoſe too Numerous enough, to ſway the Nation to conſent to their aboliſhing.</p>
               <p>I have ſaid already that, upon the ſuppoſition of this Security, there can be nothing but private <hi>Ambition or Avarice</hi> capable to raiſe an oppoſition againſt this generous Deſign of Univerſal Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. But ſurely no <hi>Private</hi> Intereſt wil he capable to bear up long againſt the <hi>General</hi> Intereſt of the Nation. Now it has been often a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſerted by many, and demonſtrated with great evidence, that thoſe whoſe Intereſt it is to deſire Liberty, are far more nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than thoſe that oppoſe it. But if in that there ſhould at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent be any miſtake, I am ſure, that when once this Liberty ſhal be eſtabliſhed, it wil then be wholy and indiſputably the Intereſt of al parties to maintain it. Al the ſeveral Intereſts of the Nation wil be then drawn up into one Circle, and the Extremitys wil touch each other. The <hi>Church of England</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,</hi> how oppoſite ſoever in other reſpects, wil therby becom inſeparably cimented into one Common Caus. And, tho we ſhould ſuſpect the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> to have contrary Inclinations, yet the Strength of the others Union wil oblige them, for their own Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to concur in promoting the general Good.</p>
               <p>Yet for al this, I wil not ſtick to acknowledg that this ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of an inclination to Perſecute, <hi>in any that may be uppermoſt,</hi> is not altogether unreaſonable. The Examples of <hi>Perſecutions</hi> rais'd at one time or other, by <hi>al Partys</hi> that have had the power to do it, authorize thoſe Fears. But for that very reaſon, I ſay that this is <hi>the fitteſt time</hi> that ever we can expect, to <hi>ſettle this Liberty</hi> in <hi>England:</hi> becauſe the <hi>Power</hi> is now in the Hands of the <hi>weakeſt Party,</hi> which is therfore leaſt able to ſtrain it. And if once that <hi>Settlement</hi> be made, the <hi>united Intereſt</hi> of al Partys in the Advantages it brings along with it, wil in human appearance <hi>ſecure</hi> it againſt the poſſibility of ever being ſhaken hereafter.</p>
               <p>Theſe Conſiderations, you ſee, afford a ſecond Proſpect of our Security in the eſtabliſhment of a Law of Liberty; in that it wil be the Intereſt of al Partys to maintain it: And they afford alſo an Incitement to ſet about that Work; becaus of the ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of the opportunity: Which things deſerv exceedingly to be attended unto. But after ſo palpable a demonſtration, as I think I have given, of that Security, in the Frame of the Law it ſelf, I have no mind now to intertain you with any thing that may appear more ſpeculative, tho in effect it be no leſs ſolid.</p>
               <p>My meaning in this is, that I have ſhown onely the <hi>Poſſibility of this Security.</hi> But whether or no it wil be juſt granted in the manner that I conceiv it, is what I cannot anſwer for. <hi>I rather hope it wil be made much better.</hi> But however, after this plain ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the poſſibility of the thing, I think I may reſume what I ſaid in my firſt Letter, as an Advice of ſome weight; That, in this Conjucture, it is both the <hi>Duty</hi> and the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the Nation to put this buſineſs to a <hi>Trial,</hi> in a Grave and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Parliament; and not by any means to make that impoſſible, by <hi>Faction, Jealouſy,</hi> or <hi>Deſpair,</hi> which ſeems eaſily obtainable by <hi>a prudent Conduct.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let this be our conſtant Aim, to have <hi>Liberty ſetled by a Law.</hi> That is the Mark that I ſhoot at. And I would be very loath that other Peoples Errors, or Humors, ſhould make me miſs it. We ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be ſingly intent upon our own Duty; and if we keep ſo, we cannot fail to know it. Which way ſoever we turn our Reflections, in theſe matters of Politics, they wil always bring us back to the ſame Center. The <hi>General Good</hi> is the Rule and Touch-Stone, by which al muſt be tryed and meaſured. That General Good can never be attended unto, much leſs procured, without the <hi>General Satisfaction</hi> of al Parties; Nor that Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction without this <hi>Equal and General Liberty</hi> which I have been pleading for.</p>
               <p>Now therfore that every one may the more eaſily diſcern their own Duty, while we ar in this evident poſſibility of obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch an equal and ſecure Liberty; I would have the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in the firſt place, Conſider with how much Juſtice the Odium of <hi>a Self-intereſſed and Sordid Partiality,</hi> wil be caſt upon Her by al Men, in caſe She ſtil continu to obſtruct it. <hi>Let Her conſider that, and be Aſhamed.</hi> In the next place, If the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters</hi> ſhould ſuffer themſelves to be fooled out of this Liberty, by the cunning of their Old Adverſarys; I would have them Conſider how obnoxious they yet ly, even at this very hour, to the <hi>Redoubled Laſhes of the ſame Laws</hi> under which they have ſo long groaned. <hi>Let Them conſider that, and Tremble.</hi> And if the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> ſhould ever attempt to overſtrain the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages they may receiv by this Liberty, when it ſhal be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; I would have them Conſider that in gaping for the <hi>Shadow,</hi> they wil be in danger to loſe the <hi>Subſtance. Let Them conſider that, and be Wiſe.</hi> I have now don. I onely again beg of you to pardon the tediouſneſs of <hi>Al theſe Conſiderations.</hi> and to believ me to be moſt ſincerely and affectionately Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and Sold, by <hi>Andrew Sowle,</hi> at the <hi>Three Keys,</hi> in <hi>Nags-Head-Court,</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Conduit,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
